It is worth remembering that although
Japan is no longer the world's second
largest economy, it still controls
technological choke points that are
becoming especially important in the
emerging AI revolution. Ulrike Schaede
of the University of California
described this phenomenon as Japan in
sign. Japanese consumer brands may no
longer be as dominant as they once were,
but parts of Japanese industry have
moved deeper into the production chain.
Japanese companies account for around
53% of the global silicon wafer market,
80% of photoresists, and 88% of the
photoresist coating and developing
equipment. Replacing these products
requires time, expertise, and close
cooperation with chip manufacturers.
Tokyo is therefore trying to turn the
position of its companies into an
instrument of economic security. The
2022 National Security Strategy
explicitly calls for reducing excessive
dependence on individual countries while
building the quote superiority and
indispensability of Japanese
technologies.